Okay בוקר טוב *boker tov*. Today's דף daf *daf* is ט"ו *tet
vav*, we take up let's start again from the גמרא Gemara *gemara*
on the bottom of יד עמוד ב *yud dalet amud bet*. The
משנה Mishnah *mishna* had told us a story about a child, a
young girl that was raped,
and the position of רבי יוחנן בן נורי *Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri*
was that if most of the people in the city are those
that even that if a if they had sex with the woman,
the woman would still be כשרה לכהונה *ksheira lekehunah*, which means that
they were Jewish and not, you know, ממזרים *mamzeirim* and חללים *chalalim*
and so on, which would be a normal case, then she is
כשרה *ksheira* for כהונה *kehuna*. So here we introduce the idea of
רוב Rov *rov*, but the גמרא Gemara *gemara* immediately questions that until
now we've had the debate of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel*
and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua? *Rabbi Yehoshua*, which it all had to
do with her claim and the question of percentages was immaterial. So
let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara *gemara* says, אמר ליה רבא
לרב נחמן *amlei Rava le-Rav Nachman*, so רבא *Rava* said to רב
Rav נחמן *Rav Nachman*, לרבי יוחנן בן נורי דאמר כמאן *le-Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri damar kman*, who's he going like? אי רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel, אפילו ברוב פסולין נמי מכשיר *ei Rabban Gamliel afilu berov psulin
nami machshir*, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* we said even if
a majority in the neighborhood are פסולין *psulin*, like the case of
a married woman or non-Jews,
then he would still say it's okay if she says that she
knows the man and the man was okay. אי רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua. אפילו ברוב כשירים נמי פסול pasul *ei Rabbi Yehoshua afilu berov
ksheirim nami pasul*, and like רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua*, even
if most are invalid, it's still going to be פסול *pasul*. Now
of course an obvious answer here is that here she didn't have
a claim, she didn't know who the man was and therefore she
needed the רוב Rov, *rov*. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* sort of works
that issue through, but תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says maybe the גמרא Gemara
*gemara* assumes she did know who the man was, but anyway that's
the גמרא Gemara *gemara*'s question. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
*gemara*'s answer is. אמר ליה הכי אמר רב Rav יהודה אמר רב
Rav *amlei hachi amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, this is what רב
יהודה *Rav Yehuda* says in the name of רב *Rav*, top of
ט"ו עמוד א *tet vav amud aleph*, בקרונות של ציפורי Tzipori, היה
מעשה *bikoronot shel Tzippori haya maaseh*, the story was with the caravans,
the wagons of ציפורי Tzipori *Tzippori*. What does that mean? It means
that there was a there were caravans passing through and therefore what?
So let's take a look. וכדרבי אמי *u'k'Rabbi Ami*, like what רבי
אמי *Rabbi Ami* said. דאמר רבי אמי והוא שהייתה סיעה שבני אדם
כשירים עוברת לשם *d'amar Rabbi Ami vehu she-hayeta siya she-bnei adam ksheirim
overet l'sham*, that it when a so he apparently qualifies the משנה
Mishnah. *mishna*, that that's when there was a group of people passing
through there, כשירים *ksheirim* people, meaning people that even if they had
sex with her would not have made her invalid. וכדרבי ינאי *u'k'Rabbi
Yannai*, so we're still not clear what that does, so it's like
what רבי ינאי *Rabbi Yannai* says. דאמר רבי ינאי נבעלה בקרונות כשירה
לכהונה *d'amar Rabbi Yannai niv'ela bikronot ksheira l'kehuna*, if she has has
had sex in the in the wagons, she's כשירה לכהונה *ksheira l'kehuna*.
The גמרא Gemara *gemara* says, בקרונות סלקא דעתך *bikronot sakadatach*? What do
I care if she had sex in the wagons or not? So
אלא Ela נבעלה בשעת קרונות כשירה לכהונה *ela niv'ela bishat kronot ksheira
l'kehuna*, if she had sex at the time when the wagons, when
the caravans were passing through. Right. Now why does any of this
matter? So let's keep on going and we will find out soon.
אבל פירש parush. אחד מציפורי ובעל *aval piresh echad mi-Tzippori u'ba'al*,
but if just a somebody came from the town and met her
out in the fields and yes, even though they're רוב Rov. כשירים
*rov ksheirim*, we'll we'll figure this all out, but if she basically
met some guy left his home and they and they met in
the fields and she had sex with him and it was not
at the time that these caravans were passing through and it might
not have been from one of the guys from the caravan, we
know it was from one of the guys from ציפורי Tzipori, *Tzippori*,
then הולד שתוקי *havlad shtuki*, the child is a שתוקי *shtuki*, which
is again a child of questionable parenting and of therefore problematic status,
he might be, you know, and
again if that would mean that we're also concerned that the man
might have been a ממזר mamzer. *mamzer*, might have been a חלל
*chalal*, and therefore she's invalid as well, okay. So why does any
of this matter? All we know is now, okay, you've said it
twice or three times, it needed to be caravans passing through, if
it was from some guy in the town you've got a problem
even though it's רוב Rov *rov*, why? So finally let's get finally
to the explanation. כי הא דכי אתא רב דימי מארץ ישראל Yisrael.
*ki hai de-ki ata Rav Dimi me-Eretz Yisrael*, like that story when
רב דימי *Rav Dimi* came from ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, he said
in the name of זעירי אמר רבי חנינא *Zeiri amar Rabbi Chanina*.
ואמרי לה אמר זעירי אמר רבי חנינא *v'amlei amar Zeiri amar Rabbi
Chanina*, and some say it was a straight tradition of זעירי *Zeiri*
and רבי חנינא *Rabbi Chanina*, it wasn't through רב דימי *Rav Dimi*.
הולכין אחר רוב rov העיר ואין הולכין אחר רוב rov סיעה *holchin
achar rov ha-ir v'ein holchin achar rov siya*, you go by the
majority of the people in the city, not the majority of the
people in the caravan, which is different than we just said, we
just said the caravan helps. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says, כלפי
לייא *klapei laya*? Which way is this going? Like it doesn't make
any sense. And now we're going to finally get to the key
factor here. הני ניידי והני קבי וקיימי *hani naydi v'hani kvi v'kaimi*,
the caravan is moving, the people in the city are fixed, standing.
Why does any of that matter? They're in their fixed place. אלא
ella, הולכין אחר רוב rov העיר והוא דאיכא רוב rov סיעה בהדה
*ela holchin achar rov ha-ir vehu de'ika rov siya bahada*, you go
by the majority of the city plus the majority of the caravan.
Now what difference does any of this make? Who cares if it's
the majority of the city plus the majority of the caravan? It
still winds up to be just majority likely that's going to happen.
So what the גמרא Gemara *gemara* has finally alluded to and it's
going to say more explicitly in a minute, but I need to
finally explain to you what's going on, it's this principle of כל
דקבוע כמחצה על מחצה kemechtza al mechtza. דמי כל דפריש מרובא פריש
Kol d'parish me-rubah parish. *kol de'kavuah k'mechtza al mechtza dami kol de'parish
me-ruba parish*, which is a bizarre idea in terms of, you know,
percentages, it doesn't make any statistical sense, but the idea is that
when something is in its fixed place and you're trying to identify
what it is, you have to treat it like a fifty-fifty. If
something separated out from a group and you want to know its
identity, then you go by the majority. So the classic case of
is that if you find a piece of meat we're going to
have in the middle of the out on the street and you
want to know which butcher did it come from and there are
nine כשר Kosher butchers and one non-כשר Kosher butcher, so nine out
of ten most likely it came from a כשר Kosher. butcher you
can assume the piece of meat is כשר. Kosher. It's פריש, Parish,
it's separated from the butcher store, and therefore you just want to
know which one it came from, you go by the majority. However,
let's say you come home and the piece of meat is on
you and you don't remember where you bought it. Now, that's a
fairly similar question, I mean the meat isn't in the store, but
somehow that's a little bit of different because there, again, this all
becomes very formalistic, you're not starting with the meat and saying like,
where did this meat come from? Somehow in that case because the
meat, you're asking yourself like, which store did I go to? Again,
even there I can't exactly explain to you why that's different, but
there you're asking like, which store did I walk into? So those
stores were in a fixed place and you want to know which
one of those stores I entered into I was in this afternoon,
so that's identifying something in its fixed location and therefore we say
we have to treat it like a 50/50. I don't even begin
to understand the logic behind this, okay, it's hard enough to understand
what falls in a פריש Parish category, what falls in a קבוע
Kavuah category. Similarly here, let's take the case like this:
if a man came from, which actually is the גמרא Gemara is
actually going to ask, because even if a guy comes from ציפורי,
Tzipori. he leaves his house and him and this woman they meet
somewhere out in the fields or whatever, so that's also he's פריש,
Parish, he's not קבוע Kavuah and so on. So it might be
that that case actually is a case of פריש, Parish, but let's
say she goes and she has sex with him in his house,
okay, and she doesn't know, that would be an easier case of
קבוע. Kavuah. So she doesn't know which guy's house she went to,
okay, so that's קבוע, Kavuah, everybody has like a fixed location and
you're trying to figure out is it this, is it this, is
it that, so because everything is like a fixed location you treat
it as 50/50. It's only because that there is a, it's when
they leave the house and you want to know where did he
come from and who is he, then you go by the רוב
rov, and you say רוב ארכיבו. Rov archeivo. But even if that
all is true and even if we accept that, presumably by the
way to some degree the logic is,
to some degree the logic is is that if this is just
a question of like what's the identity of this meat, well, ninety
percent likely it's כשר. Kosher, What's the identity of the man or
the status of the man that this woman had sex with? Ninety-nine,
ninety-five percent likely he was כשר, Kosher, fine he's כשר, Kosher. כל
דפריש מרובא פריש. Kol d'parish me-rubah parish But if I'm actually looking
at things like a fixed set of things of objects here, I've
got like this fixed set of objects and I'm trying to say
like, okay,
like what is like this guy's status? And I'm looking and it's
within a collection,
if I've actually looked at and I have like a fixed set
of objects and I'm looking at one of them and I want
to know what the story is, to some degree I can't ignore
the fact that among this set are things that are problematic as
well. So the fact that I'm dealing with a fixed set of
a finite number of objects and I'm looking at one of them
and trying to figure out its identity, but the one I'm looking
at might be the problematic one, there definitely is the problematic one
in this set. So that forces me to acknowledge, to sort of
make it a ספק, Safek, as opposed to if I'm just looking
like something here and I want to say what's the
status, oh well most likely, I'm not looking at a set of
things among which there's definitely the problematic among them. That seems to
be some, if that gives you a little bit of a beginning
of a way of making sense of this.
Better off saying
that it doesn't make sense, okay, fine.
That was a really, no, I've seen that was like a very
clear explanation. The endemic problem is you could use that explanation and
switch it. In other words, looking at the set, I should look
at the set the way that it is and I should go
by רוב, rov
right,
most of the things in front of me are כשר.
kosher Exactly, that's exactly right.
Alright, so anyway I don't really understand it, back to that, so
anyway,
but the point is is that fine, if it wasn't in the
guy's home, if it was פריש אחד מציפורי, Parish echad mi-Tzipori, that's
also called פריש. Parish. So the גמרא Gemara is going to say
that and the גמרא Gemara in the end is going to say
that here you actually have a double רוב. rov On the one
hand it might have been from ציפורי Tzipori and then we'd say
כל דפריש מרובא פריש Kol d'parish me-rubah parish. and it's רוב כשר.
Rov kasher. On the other hand it might have been from the
caravans and we'd say כל דפריש מרובא פריש. kol d'parush meruba parush,
And again statistically I'm not exactly sure why that makes it better,
right, like if you just did the odds it was 90% in
each way, so if you just had one רוב rov. it would
be 90% likely. So if you had the other, if it came
from ציפורי, 90% likely. If it came from the caravans, also 90%
likely. So the likelihood is I have to do the math. The
likelihood that it's a problem, it's good, I don't even can't figure
out the math. Anyway, it's not clear to me that the numbers
make a difference, they probably don't, but the גמרא Gemara is going
to say. say that the reason you need the double רוב rov
is for the following reason, not really logically it makes it percentage-wise
better. The reason you need the double רוב rov is that the
caravan is always going to be פירש. parush The caravan is traveling
through even if as the גמרא Gemara graphically said before she had
sex on the wagon, it's considered פירש parush because the caravan is
not nobody's in their fixed home location. Somehow that's always considered they're
always פירש parush. from their home from where from their hometown. So
therefore that ensures that you like like the idea it reminds you
that you need it to be a scenario of פירש. parush, Whereas
if you basically said if one guy from the city separated off
and had sex with her, then she's okay because it's פירש, parush.
that might lead you to say it's okay if she goes and
has sex with him in his house. Okay, so the whole thing
here of the need for the caravan and the need for the
double רוב rov, is because the caravan is always a scenario of
פירש. parush, Whereas if you just had the normal case of the
רוב rov, of the city, you would come to say, oh we're
going to allow it when the guy leaves his home, we're going
to allow it if it winds up being sex in his home
as well. Okay, so let's just read that a minute and then
we'll ask and have any questions. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אלא הכי נאמר רוב העיר ואיכא רוב סיעה בהדה, Ela
hochinach rov hair vehudi ika rov siyah bahada, the majority of the
city when you have the majority also of the people passing through,
דאין הולכין
אחר רוב העיר גרידא, de'ein hochinach rov hair greda, you don't just
go by the majority of the city, ולא אחר רוב סיעה גרידתא,
velo achar rov siyah gredata, or just a majority of a caravan.
מאי טעמא, mai tama, גזירה רוב סיעה אטו רוב העיר. gezeira rov
siyah atu rov hair.
If you just allow to go by the majority of the caravan,
which makes sense,
you'll come to allow a case where you just go by the
majority of the city.
Okay, and why is that a problem?
So the גמרא Gemara says, רוב העיר נמי, rov hair nami, אי
דקא אזלי אינהו לגבה, i deka azli inhu lagabah, if they leave
their home and go and meet her, כל דפריש מרובא פריש, kol
d'parish me-ruba parish, so again we're back to רוב, rov? they left
their home. לא צריכא דקא אזלה היא לגבייהו, lo tzricha deka azla
i legabeihu, she would go to them. דהוה ליה קבוע, dehavei lei
kavua, because that would be a קבוע. kavua. ואמר רבי זירא כל
קבוע כמחצה
על מחצה דמי, v'amar Rabi Zeira kol kavua kemechtza al mechtza dami,
every קבוע kavua is כמחצה על מחצה. ke-mechetza al mechetza, Now רש"י
Rashi has a slightly different גירסא, girsa, רש"י's Rashi גירסא girsa is
not כגון דאזלה היא לגבייהו, kegon de'azla i legabeihu, but איכא דקא
אזלה היא לגבייהו. ika deka azla i legabeihu.
Sometimes she will go to their home. And therefore we can never
allow ourselves to go by the רוב rov. of the city because
we will if we allow that we'll come to allow not just
a case of פירש, parush. but we'll allow a case of קבוע.
kavua. So therefore since the city based on the scenario sometimes it's
okay sometimes it's not, we're going to say you never just go
by the majority of the city, you always also need this idea
of this caravan passing through. So this is this idea of a
קבוע kavua versus פירש. parush. Number two, in principle you really should
be totally okay going by רוב rov. of the city when it's
not in the guy's home. But because that's easily confused where it
happens and that sort of and that you'll come to make a
mistake and you'll come to mix them up, we insist that there
also be this other majority of the caravan which is always a
scenario of פירש. parush Just one more thing which is, so how
does this fit in to the whole debate of רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel and רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua, Who is this an answer according
to?
So תוספות says maybe you even need it for רבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel maybe the woman isn't making a claim that she knows who
the guy is etc. etc. רש"י Rashi says all of this is
according to רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua, So then it becomes very important
because you'll remember yesterday that the גמרא Gemara said רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel focuses on her claim. If she makes a claim, great. If
not, you know then it's problematic even maybe like I don't know
a double ספק. safek. So רש"י Rashi says that this is an
answer where she isn't making a claim who the guy is, but
it still is okay even according to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua who
normally is very strict in this scenario where you've got this like
double רוב. rov? And she's not making a claim. And she doesn't
know who the guy is, but even so it's still okay because
you've got this רוב rov or a double רוב rov? and so
on and who knows, that might be good even according you know
according to רבן גמליאל as well. Okay, so here the גמרא Gemara
doesn't well certainly רש"י Rashi says this is רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua
but the גמרא Gemara said רבן גמליאל maybe more demands the claim
and more focuses on the claim. So it's not exactly clear how
this works out for רבן גמליאל and רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua but
here we have a case where we go by the majority and
in principle you should go by one majority, but because it gets
confusing in this פירש peirush, and קבוע kavua issue we do this
double majority. Yes, Michael.
So does there have to be like a real good chance now
that whoever she was with was with this caravan, I mean it
can't be a caravan of like five people in a city of
a hundred.
Yeah, I don't think so. I don't think that it has to
create a high level of ספק safek that it happened from the
caravan because in the end the way the גמרא Gemara at least
is framing it is that it's just to so you shouldn't come
to be like you know it's like a גזירה. gezeira. So you
shouldn't come to be lenient in a case when it was a
case of קבוע. kavua. But in principle you really are allowed to
go by the majority of the city. Yeah.
The whole issue is whether she's permissible to a כהן? Kohen? Yes,
yes.
I mean there's a related issue about whether the if she gets
pregnant as a result whether the child you know you have to
be concerned is the child permissible to a כהן Kohen is the
child a ספק ממזר? safek mamzer?
Right, well by the child it also might be a question of
ממזר. mamzer. Right, because if the guy who who raped her or
you know is a ממזר.
Right, but it has to be some whatever that would be, but
you're so you're saying that I mean it has some chance as
opposed to like you
know...
Presumably, right.
But not like overwhelmingly likely.
Yeah, yeah. I think because it's basically the way it's being framed
is it's just a גזירה. gezeira. Yeah, Dov.
First of all maybe... I'm
imposing assumptions that are not warranted, but the גמרא Gemara could have
said that in the case of this of אחרונות, achranos, it's like
people in the city
wouldn't... we're talking about rape here, we're talking about cases where these
grifters are more likely to have done it. Right, I was wondering
about that too.
Yeah, it's just to follow what we're talking about here because the
משנה Mishnah is talking about a particular case and she went down
to the well, she's not in
the center of the town and then somehow it kind of morphs
into, it's hard to follow
how it's become this very special case.
Right, well, because the point is that this was seen as like,
really, so this the general rule or not? And really every case
is a single ספק? safek? And maybe the answer is yes, it's
enough that there's a רוב, rov, but the גמרא Gemara obviously was
resisting that,
so it came up with a case where there was a special
circumstance. Now in the end we're about to see another approach, which
is I know a hard read to the משנה. Mishnah. We're about
to see another approach which is basically going to acknowledge that the
משנה Mishnah, was like a הוראת שעה horat sha'ah and we shouldn't
learn הלכה halakhah from it, which is another way of dealing with
it, but one way or the other it seems the גמרא Gemara
doesn't want to sort of draw the immediate הלכתי halakhic conclusion from
the משנה. Mishnah Okay, so let's take a look. First now we're
going to establish this principle of קבוע kavuah and רוב, rov. okay?
So this is one of the major גמרות Gemaras which deals with
it. So גמרא Gemara
says ומי בעינן תרי רובי? u-mi ba'inan trei robei? Do you really
need a double רוב? rov. והתניא, ve-hatanya, and we taught in a
ברייתא, Baraisa, תשע חנויות, tesha chanuyos, here is your classic case of
קבוע kavuah and מחצה על מחצה, mechtza al mechtza, nine stores, כולן
מוכרות בשר שחוטה, kulan mocheros basar shechutah, they all sell slaughtered meat,
ואחת מוכרת בשר נבלה, ve-achat mocheres basar neveilah, and one sells non-slaughtered
meat, ולקח מאחת מהן ואינו יודע מאיזו מהן לקח, ve-lakach me-achas me-hen
ve-eino yodei'a me-eizo me-hen lakach, and you purchased from one and you
don't remember which store you went into, ספק אסור, safek asur, that's
prohibited, that's קבוע. kavuah. You don't remember which store you went into,
so the ספק safek is to some degree framed not in terms
of the store, in terms of the meat, but in terms of
the store. What store did I go into? And the store is
in its fixed location. ובנמצא, u-ve-nimtza, but if I found the piece
of meat, הלך אחר הרוב, halach achar ha-rov, then you go by
majority because then the question is what store did I go into,
but what is the status of the meat? To determine the status
of the meat I think about the number of stores, but it's
a question about the meat and therefore that's considered פריש parish and
therefore you go by רוב. rov Okay, so that's the classic paradigm
of כל דקבוע כמחצה על מחצה דמי וכל דפריש מרובא פריש, kol
d'kavuah k'mechtza al mechtza dami ve-chol d'parish me-ruba parish, but the point
the גמרא Gemara is making is you only need one רוב. rov
Since when do you need a double רוב? rov So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, so the
גמרא Gemara. says וכי תימא בשאין דלתות מדינה נעולות, ve-chi teima be-she-ein
daltot medinah ne'ulos, maybe it's a case where the gates of the
city aren't locked and therefore anytime there's meat there it might have
come from somebody traveling from outside the city, דקאתי ליה רובא מעלמא,
de-ka-ati lei ruba me-alma, so it came from the larger world, sort
of like the traveling caravans, not always פריש. parish. There's always a
second רוב rov in addition to which store it came from, there's
the possibility it came from somebody passing through, like the passing through
caravans, so maybe it's a double
רוב? rov. The meat case. The classic case of the meat is
you don't need a double רוב, rov, you need your classic single
רוב. rov. So why are we saying we need the caravan passing
through here? So the גמרא Gemara says well maybe we'll construct the
meat case like the caravan case, that the doors of the city
are open and therefore there are people passing through and maybe it
came from somebody passing through. So the גמרא Gemara says והאמר רבי
זירא, ve-ha-amar Rabbi Zeira, אף על פי שדלתות מדינה נעולות, af al
pi she-daltot medinah ne'ulos, no, but רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said that
even if the doors of the city are locked and you know
it came from one of the stores in the city and it
did not come anywhere else, nevertheless we say you go by רוב.
rov, So why by the meat do you go by the רוב
rov, and why by this case of the rape do you need
there to be another caravan passing through? So the גמרא Gemara says
מעלה עשו ביוחסין. ma'alah asu be-yuchsin. Again we're having an extra stringency
when it comes to the idea of marrying a woman off to
a כהן kohen and therefore we are not going by the normal
rules. So the normal rules is we say כל דפריש מרובא פריש,
kol de-parish mi-rubba parish, we're not afraid that it's going to lead
to a קבוע kavuah case, we just say you go by רוב
rov. and end of story, but here because it's a case of
יוחסין yuchsin and marrying the woman off to a כהן, kohen, we're
extra strict and therefore we demand that there be this second רוב
rov as well. גופא, gufa, let's take a look further. אמר רבי
זירא, amar Rabbi Zeira, כל קבוע כמחצה על מחצה דמי, kol kavuah
k'mechtza al mechtza dami, any time it's fixed it's treated like fifty-fifty,
בין לקולא בין לחומרא, bein le-kula bein le-chumra, whether to be lenient
or stringent, because he said כל קבוע, kol kavuah, so until now
we've been assuming stringency, that if even if there are nine כשר
stores you have to say it's a ספק אסור safek asur if
it's a קבוע. kavuah. Even if the majority of the city is
כשרים ksheirim you have to say it's maybe it's פסול if it's
קבוע. kavuah. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara assumes you said כל קבוע
kol kavuah so we would even be lenient. So we're going to
sort of explore that, is it true we'd even be lenient in
a case of כל קבוע? kol kavuah? So what's the case? So
the case would be like
this... מנא ליה לרבי זירא הא? mena lei le-Rabbi Zeira ha? Where
does he get this from? אילימא מתשע חנויות Ilima mi-tesha chanuyot כולן
מוכרות בשר שחוטה ואחת בשר נבלה. kullan mocherot basar shechuta ve-achat basar
nevela. The store, the case about the nine kosher stores and the
one non-kosher store ולקח מאחת מהן ואינו יודע מאיזו מהן לקח ve-lakach
mei-achat me-hen ve-eino yodeia mei-eizo me-hen lakach and you purchased from one
and you don't know which one, ספיקו אסור, sfeiko assur, it's forbidden.
ובנמצא הלך אחר הרוב, u-venimtza halach achar ha-rov, but if it's found
on the street, it's you go by the majority, so התם לחומרא.
hatam le-chumra. There you're being strict. When it's קבוע kavuah you don't
know which store you went in, then it's even though there are
nine kosher stores, you're strict. So there it's like כמחצה על מחצה,
ke-mechetza al mechetza but it's being strict. That doesn't prove you lenient.
אלא מתשעה צפרדעים. Ela mi-tesha tzfardeim. You have nine frogs ושרץ אחד
ביניהם ve-sheretz echad benei-hem and one שרץ, sheretz, one rodent that actually
causes טומאה tumah among them. Frogs don't cause טומאה. tumah. ונגע באחד
מהן Ve-naga be-achad me-hen and you touched one of them ואיני יודע
באיזה מהן נגע. Ve-eini yodeia be-eizeh me-hen naga. You don't know which
one you touched. So that's a case of קבוע, kavuah, right? It's
not like one animal separated from the bunch and you touched it
and you don't know what it is. It's they're all in the
set, they're all a group of ten and you just touched one
of the ten and you don't know which one you touched. So
in that case ספיקו טמא. sfeiko tamei. If it's a doubt and
it's טמא. tamei. So התם נמי לחומרא. hatam nami le-chumra. There also
we're being strict because nine of them are non-טמא tamei and we're
being strict. אלא fine, the following case, this is a תוספתא בטהרות,
Tosefta be-Taharot, meaning we're not just making these cases up, we're saying
that this is a Tannaitic source here. It's a תוספתא בטהרות. Tosefta
be-Taharot. אלא מתשעה שרצים וצפרדע אחד ביניהם. Ela mi-tesha sheratzim ve-tzfardei echad
benei-hem. The reverse. Nine שרצים, sheratzim, nine rodents that cause טומאה tumah
and one frog. Dead? Yes, dead. ונגע באחת מהן Ve-naga be-achat me-hen
and you touched one of them ואינו יודע במה נגע. Ve-eino yodeia
be-ma naga. You don't know which one you touched. Now now it's
90% likely you're טמא. tamei. Nevertheless what do we say? But they're
all fixed, right? They're all there in the group. Okay, so we
say ברשות היחיד ספיקו טמא. bi-reshut ha-yachid sfeiko tamei. If it's in
a private domain you are the doubt you have a doubt and
it makes you טמא. tamei. ברשות הרבים ספיקו טהור. Bi-reshut ha-rabbim sfeiko
tahor. If you're in a public domain even with your doubt you
can assume that you are טהור. tahor. This is a general principle
by טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-tahara that doubts that arise in private domain
in a private space are considered you you are you assume you're
טמא, tamei, in a public space you assume you're טהור. tahor. Why
exactly that's true is another one of these things, I mean this
is one דף daf of seemingly very arbitrary types of rules in
terms of dealing with ספקות. sfekot. That is learned from, just to
make it even more complicated, that's learned from סוטה. Sotah. Because since
the תורה Torah refers to a woman who sleeps with another man
as והיא נטמאה, ve-hi nitma'ah, she became טמאה. tmeiah. So when do
you assume she became טמאה tmeiah when there's a ספק? safek? When
she went into seclusion. But if she was only seen with the
man in public you wouldn't assume she became טמאה. tmeiah. This becomes
the basis for saying that if there is a doubt of טומאה
tumah in private it is טמא tamei and if it is in
public it is not. So anyway but it has to be a
but it has to be a doubt. So here you have a
case where it's 90% likely you touched a dead rodent. Under any
normal circumstance we wouldn't say that's a ספק. safek. We'd say you're
ודאי טמא. vadai tamei. End of the story. But no, we consider
it a ספק, safek, כמחצה על מחצה ke-mechetza al mechetza and therefore
we'll make you טהור tahor in רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim. So here
you see the principle כל קבוע כמחצה על מחצה kol kavuah ke-mechetza
al mechetza is even lenient even though nine of these are dead
rodents and make you טמא, tamei, you are nevertheless and you would
you should assume you're טמא. tamei. We're going to treat it as
a ספק safek and because we treat it as a ספק, safek,
we let you be טהור tahor in רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim. So
that's the principle כל קבוע...
kol kavuah... because of רשות היחיד? reshut ha-yachid?
Because the סוטה Sotah was in private? Yes, because in private. So
therefore so that's the principle כל קבוע כמחצה על מחצה kol kavuah
ke-mechetza al mechetza even to create a ספק safek when the majority
would say that it's a problem, this says it's not a definite
problem, it's only a ספק safek and therefore that will allow for
leniency. Okay, so therefore that shows us that idea. I'm just going
to finish this thought and then everybody can ask questions that's been
backing up. So now we have proved that the classic paradigm of
the nine kosher stores is כל קבוע כמחצה על מחצה kol kavuah
ke-mechetza al mechetza but that's only לחומרא. le-chumra. The גמרא Gemara makes
a point of pointing out that it would be true even לקולא.
le-kula. If nine were bad and one were good like nine were
טמא tamei and one was not טמא, tamei, it would still be
a ספק safek and the benefit of being a ספק safek is
that it allows you to say by טומאה, tumah, ספק טומאה ברשות
הרבים טהור. safek tumah bi-reshut ha-rabbim tahor. You could also imagine a
case where it's דרבנן. de-rabbanan. So even if the majority would point
you to איסור, issur, since we have the idea of כל קבוע
כמחצה על מחצה kol kavuah ke-mechetza al mechetza it's a ספק safek
and then you could say ספק דרבנן לקולא. safek de-rabbanan le-kula. Let's
say for example it wasn't selling בשר נבלה. basar nevela. Let's say
it was selling, I don't know, it was selling a chicken that
was cooked with milk. Okay, so an איסור דרבנן, issur de-rabbanan, right?
So you would say even if nine of them were selling the
chicken cooked with milk and one was selling the chicken not cooked
with milk, okay, so it's כל קבוע כמחצה על מחצה kol kavuah
ke-mechetza al mechetza and therefore ספק דרבנן, safek de-rabbanan, ספק דרבנן לקולא.
safek de-rabbanan le-kula. At least in theory you could say that. So
we treat it as a ספק safek even לקולא le-kula even if
the nine are going in the negative direction out of the ten.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this so that's the principle
of כל דפריש מרובא פריש, כל קבוע כמחצה על מחצה kol kavuah
ke-mechetza al mechetza and that the כמחצה על מחצה is even
לקולא. le-kula. ומדאורייתא מנלן? U-mide-oraita minlan? Now where do you get this
is obviously a biblical principle, I mean we're applying it to biblical
ideas, כשרות kashrut and טומאה, tumah, so where does this come from
the תורה? Torah? So אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says, וארב
לו וקם עליו. Ve-arav lo ve-kam alav. So this is... is talking
about committing murder, lies in wait and rises up against him. So
what do we learn from that פסוק? pasuk? עד שיתכוון לו, ad
sheyiskavein lo, that you have to intend to kill the guy you
killed. This is the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the
גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. What happens if you tried to kill
ראובן Reuven and accidentally you killed שמעון? Shimon? Is that considered to
be a case of מזיד meizid or a case of שוגג? shogeg?
So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that would be a case of
שוגג. shogeg. You're only liable for murder, right? I mean in our
law we might distinguish it between first degree murder and manslaughter, okay,
but for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon it's only murder if you kill
the guy you're intending to kill. The רבנן Rabbanan say no, even
if you intended to kill ראובן Reuven and you killed שמעון Shimon
it's still murder. So what do you learn from the פסוק pasuk
that says lying in wait, that sounds like you need to intend
for that guy? So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says עד שיתכוון לו,
ad sheyiskavein lo, only if you killed the guy you intended to
kill. ורבנן, Verabbanan, and what would the Rabbis say? אמר דבי רבי
ינאי, Amar dbei Rabbi Yanai, פרט לזורק אבן לגב. perat lezorek even
lego. It doesn't exclude a case of trying to kill ראובן Reuven
and kill שמעון, Shimon, it excludes a case of throwing a stone
into a group of people. We might say randomly firing into a
group of people, okay, לגב, lego, right, randomly firing into a group
of people. Now how's that different? Okay, still trying to kill ראובן
Reuven and kill שמעון. Shimon. So היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the
case? אילימא דאיכא תשעה כנעני ואחד ישראל. Ilima de'ika tisha Kena'ani ve'echad
Yisrael. Now the original גרסא girsa here was גויים, Goyim, but since
obviously the implication of this גמרא Gemara is that you are not
liable for the death penalty for killing a non-Jew,
we have self-censored the text. So you know, I mean everybody knows
this, I've mentioned this more than once, that when all the negative
גמרות Gemaros were about non-Jews, so when Jews started converting to Christianity
in the Middle Ages and told the Church about all the negative
גמרות, Gemaros, about all the גמרות Gemaros that were so offensive, so
the Church started burning the גמרא. Gemara So therefore what we did
is we went through a process of self-censorship. So we took out
all the times it says גוי Goy and we replaced it with
the word עכו"ם, Akum, right, עובדי כוכבים ומזלות, ovdei chochavim umazalos, which
means like oh this is only talking about those ancient pagans, those
star worshipers. But when the גמרא Gemara was particularly offensive,
then it was changed to כנעני. Kena'ani. So it was even more
oh, only the ancient Canaanites. Okay, so here it's כנעני, Kena'ani, but
the original גרסא girsa was גוי. Goy. So if it was what?
נכרים. Nochrim. גוי, Goy, okay, either גוי Goy or נכרים. Nochrim. Okay,
so היכי דמי, heichi dami, אילימא דאיכא תשעה כנעני ואחד ישראל ביניהם,
ilima de'ika tisha Kena'ani ve'echad Yisrael beineihem, there are nine non-Jews and
one Jew among them, so and you're saying that you're exempt, ותיפוק
ליה דרובא כנעני נינהו, vesipuk lei deruba Kena'ani ninhu, of course you're
exempt because most were non-Jews, so it's not even like you intended
right if the guy who let off one shot into the group
of people, it would be like he was we should assume it
wasn't an act of you know
towards a non-Jew. אינמי פלגא ופלגא, Inami palga upalga, even if it
was 50-50, ספק נפשות להקל, safek nefashos lehakel, we should be lenient
because there's not a presumption that the act was going to be
an act of killing a Jew. It was 50-50. לא צריכא, Lo
tzricha, so the חידוש chiddush is דאיכא תשעה ישראלים וכנעני אחד ביניהם,
de'ika tisha Yisraelim ve'Kena'ani echad beineihem, nine Jews and one non-Jew, so
he shot one random person in the group. So I should have
said that constitutes an act of shooting a Jew and therefore whoever
you shot, you're חייב chayav because it's like you tried to kill
ראובן Reuven and you killed שמעון. Shimon. So the חידוש chiddush is
that you're לא חייב. lo chayav. Why? דהוה ליה כנעני קבוע, dehavei
lei Kena'ani kavuah, because the non-Jew is fixed, וכל קבוע כמחצה על
מחצה דמי. vechol kavuah kemachetza al machetza dami. And therefore it's like
50-50, so the act is never defined, it's not trying to kill
ראובן Reuven and killing שמעון Shimon where both were Jews, it's trying
to kill one person in a group, but because there's one non-Jew
in the group it's like 50-50, so it's not defined as trying
to kill a Jew, and therefore even if you wound up killing
a Jew, you are off the hook. So that's what we learn
the principle of כל קבוע כמחצה על מחצה דמי. kol kavuah kemachetza
al machetza dami. Okay, so now we've established the principle, we've established
that it applies even לקולא, lekula, and now we've explained that in
our case even though in principle one רוב rov should be enough
if it's a case of פירש, but because of יוחסין yuchsin you
need a double רוב. rov, Yes, Michael.
But what about in the case of the butcher, you know, where
we look at that one like okay well we say that פלגא
palga whatever, but don't they also have a חזקה chazaka that they
go buy kosher meat? Why isn't that...
All right, whatever it is. You forgot, you didn't realize, your wife
told you afterwards oh don't go to that store, did I hope
you didn't go to that other store, they just lost the השגחה,
hashgacha, come on, you can come up with a circumstance. Yes, so...
but in the case of the nine rows... so it's not a
case of כל קבוע kol kavuah makes it a ספק, safek, it's
already a ספק safek because you don't know, and the question of
it being outside is the principle that trumps anything. I mean that's
a defined...
no,
because if it's 90 percent likely we wouldn't call that a ספק.
safek. A ספק safek has to be a roughly balanced ספק. safek.
So it wouldn't get into the category of ספק רשות הרבים טהור
ספק רשות היחיד טמא... safek reshus harabbim tahor safek reshus hayachid tamei...
it gets into the category
once it's 50-50 it could be called a ספק. safek.
Right, but you don't reach its conclusion because of the... because it's
in רשות... reshus...
right, you go by the location after you've categorized it as a
ספק, safek, but if it's 90 percent it's not a ספק. safek.
All right, all right, so now we figured that part out. But
now we're going to go back to this
about whether that actually was what happened in this case. איתמר, itmar,
it was taught: רבי חייא בר אבא. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba. רב
חנן בר רבא אמר רב Rav Chanan bar Rava amar Rav הוראת
שעה היתה. hora'at sha'ah hayta. No, you can't rule like that, that
was a special circumstance. Okay, now, presumably what they are assuming, that
it was not a case of double רוב, rov. but they don't
want to draw the conclusion that you can just normally rely on
a רוב. rov So therefore one says, "no, we rule that way,"
and the other says, "no, that case was a special exception, there
were other circumstances that we are not privy to and we can't
draw any conclusions from that case." מתיב רבי ירמיה, Mostiv Rabbi Yirmiya,
so רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya asks, וליוחסין לא בעינן תרי רובי? u-leyuchsin
lo bayinan tray rovei? So are you going to tell me, you
רב who says... I'm sorry, רבי חייא בר אשי Rabbi Chiya bar
Ashi in the name of רב says we rule that way, and
now we're assuming not like we just got through saying, it's not
a double רוב, rov. it's a simple case of a רוב, rov
right? That's the משנה, Mishnah all the משנה Mishnah, says it was
a single case of רוב. rov So you're going to tell me
that for יוחסין yuchsin one רוב rov is enough? Now we see
what was propelling the whole previous סוגיא. sugya. The גמרא Gemara doesn't
want to draw the conclusion from the משנה Mishnah? that one רוב
rov. is enough. והתנן, Ve-ha tnan, don't we learn in a משנה,
Mishnah top of ט"ו ע"ב, tet-vav amud bet, מצא תינוק מושלך, matza
tinok mushlach, if you find an infant, a foundling, an infant right
on the doorstep and you don't know who the parents are. אם
רוב עובדי כוכבים עובדי כוכבים. Im rov ovdei kochavim, ovdei kochavim. If
most of the people in the city are non-Jews, you assume the
infant is a non-Jew. אם רוב ישראל ישראל. Im rov Yisrael, Yisrael.
If most are Jews, you assume he's Jewish. מחצה על מחצה ישראל,
Mechtza al mechtza, Yisrael, even if it's 50-50, you assume he's Jewish.
ואמר רב, Ve-amar Rav, and we're going to have deal with this
in a minute, have fun figuring out what the implications of this
are in terms of the status. ואמר רב, Ve-amar Rav, לא שנו
אלא להחיותו. lo shanu ela l'hachyoto. That issue that you assume he's
Jewish is because of an obligation
to
sustain his life in order to take care of him, we have
an obligation וחי אחיך עמך, ve-chai achicha imach, provide for him, take
care of him, and so on. So that's what we're saying that
we'll assume that if it's 50-50 or we'll assume it's רוב, rov.
we'll assume it's ישראל.
אבל ליוחסין, Aval l'yuchsin, in terms of can this we have this
kid marry off a כהן Kohen let's say, לא. lo. Therefore we
won't assume that, okay? And we're going to need more than just
a simple רוב.
rov, ושמואל אמר
לפקח עליו את הגל, Ve-Shmuel amar, l'fake'ach alav et hagal, this is
for saving his life. So we'll deal with what שמואל Shmuel means
in a minute,
but nevertheless what you see is that you don't
go by רוב rov, for issues of marriage. So how could we
say we rule like our משנה? Mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אשתמיטיתיה הא דאמר רבי יהודה אמר רב בקרונות של ציפורי היה מעשה.
Ishtamiteih, ha d'amar Rabbi Yehuda amar Rav, bi-kronot shel Tzipori haye ma'aseh.
So he forgot what we just got through saying earlier, or that
explanation that the whole thing was a case with the wagons passing
through and the caravan passing through of ציפורי. Okay, so you understand
now we see what was going on. We see that the גמרא
Gemara did not want to draw the simple conclusion from the משנה
Mishnah that you go by רוב. rov So one explanation was to
say oh it was a special case, this caravan was passing through.
But then you have this other person says no, no, no, it's
a simple רוב rov. and maybe it was an exception, הוראת שעה
היתה, hora'at sha'ah hayta, special circumstances. Or no, maybe we actually do
פוסקין pasken like it, maybe we say a רוב rov is enough
for יוחסין. yuchsin. But then the גמרא Gemara shows why it was
resisting. Oh, we don't go by רוב rov. by יוחסין, yuchsin, you
need a double רוב. rov, Okay, must be you were confused, you
forgot that really isn't the case altogether, it was a case of
double רוב. rov. So all of this is basically finding a way
of saying don't draw the conclusion from this משנה. Mishnah We're starting
with the assumption we need a double רוב, rov. and therefore the
משנה Mishnah either was a case of a double רוב, rov? or
it was a הוראת שעה, hora'at sha'ah, but don't draw the simple
what you would think is the conclusion from the משנה Mishnah, that
one רוב rov? is enough. אשתמיטיתיה, Ishtamiteih,
he forgot, yeah, he forgot that we had got through explaining that
this case was a double רוב. rov Could be he didn't forget,
could be he didn't agree, but the גמרא Gemara is choosing to
frame it that he forgot. Of course we're not going to rule
that a single רוב rov, is enough. Either this case was הוראת
שעה היתה hora'at sha'ah hayta or it was a double רוב. rov.
But now that we're saying that they both knew it was a
double רוב, rov. and that's how one version of רב could rule
that you go by it, what's the meaning of הוראת שעה? hora'at
sha'ah?
So the גמרא Gemara says, ולרב חנן בר רבא דאמר הוראת שעה
היתה קשיא הא? u-le-Rav Chanan bar Rava d'amar hora'at sha'ah hayta, kashya
ha?
So according if you say it's הוראת שעה, hora'at sha'ah, why did
הוראת שעה? hora'at sha'ah? There was a double רוב. rov. We should
be able to go by a double רוב. rov, If he's saying
it was הוראת שעה לחומרא, hora'at sha'ah l'chumra, that you needed the
double רוב? rov. Normally you would need less? How do you explain
הוראת שעה hora'at sha'ah now that we've said it's a double רוב?
rov So the גמרא Gemara says fine, מן דמתני הא לא מתני
הא. man d'matni ha lo matni ha. The one who said that
it was in a case of a double רוב rov, would not
say it was a הוראת שעה. hora'at sha'ah. The one who says
that it was הוראת שעה hora'at sha'ah would say it wasn't a
double רוב, rov, it was a single רוב. rov. So is it
clear what the גמרא Gemara is doing? It's finding one way or
another to say don't assume from this משנה Mishnah, you can go
by a רוב. rov, Either if you say we פוסקין pasken this
משנה, Mishnah then you have to say it was the special case
of the caravans of ציפורי and it was a double רוב. rov.
Or if you have this second version, which is to say we
don't פוסקין pasken this משנה, Mishna. it was special circumstances, that's because
you're going to say it was only a single רוב, rov don't
פוסק pasken that way, it was special circumstance. And in the end
everybody's going to have the same conclusion which is. That the general
פשט pshat is that you need a double רוב. rov. So this
is how the גמרא Gemara manages to reframe the משנה Mishna so
we don't draw the conclusion that a single רוב Rov is enough.
Either it was the case of the of the caravans and we
פוסקין poskin that way because it's a double רוב, Rov, or we
don't פוסקין poskin this way, this was some special circumstances we don't
know about, don't draw any conclusions from this, you don't go by
רוב, you need a double רוב. Either way, you need a double
רוב, yes.
The passing caravan? Yes.
How's anyone going to know רוב שבי? rov shebe?
I have no idea. All right fine. Okay. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay.
One minute.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, now we get
to have the fun discussion of not knowing whether the infant is
Jewish or not Jewish, what assumptions we make. All right, outside of
יוחסין yuchsin where we have this need for a double רוב. גופא,
gufa, let's go back and look at the thing we quoted before.
מצא בו תינוק מושלך אם רוב עובדי כוכבים עובדי כוכבים אם רוב
ישראל ישראל מחצה למחצה ישראל.
matza bo tinok mushlach
im rov ovdei kochavim ovdei kochavim im rov yisrael yisrael mechtza lemechtza
yisrael. Okay. אמר רב לא שנו אלא להחיותו. amar rav lo shanu
ela lehachayoto.
When is it true that we're going to assume that if there's
a majority of Jews or fifty-fifty we'll assume he's Jewish? In terms
of our obligation to take care of him and support him. אבל
ליוחסין לא, aval leyuchsin lo, as we just got through saying, for
יוחסין yuchsin a single רוב is not enough, you're going to need
a double רוב. ושמואל אמר לפקח עליו את הגל. ushmuel amar lefakeach
alav et hagal.
No, we're going to assume he's Jewish not just to support him
but to sort of save his life on שבת. Shabbos. So the
גמרא Gemara says ומי אמר שמואל הכי? umi amar shmuel hachi? Does
שמואל Shmuel really say you need a majority before you're ready to
save his life on שבת? Shabbos? דאמר רב יוסף אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל אין הולכין בפיקוח נפש אחר הרוב. de'amar rav yosef amar
rav yehuda amar shmuel ein holchin bepikuach nefesh achar harov.
That when it comes to saving a life, you don't look at
issues of majority, even if there's a small likelihood that he is
Jewish, you would save his life. Now by the way, you could
have explained this, you know, if you wanted to be a formalist
and again also bracketing the problem that the גמרא Gemara is saying
that, you know, you don't save the life of a non-Jew on
שבת, Shabbos, which contemporary פוסקים poskim have found ways to deal with
that.
But, well, not exactly, that wouldn't have allowed חילול שבת, chilul Shabbos,
but רב משה Rav Moshe basically says if you don't save the
life of a non-Jew on שבת, Shabbos, you're risking the life of
Jews, that's his sort of workaround, and the מאירי, Meiri, yeah, they'll
try to kill you, and then the מאירי Meiri basically says to
sort of like we discussed before in terms of, but the מאירי,
Meiri, you know, in terms of how we sort of edited, you
know, censored the גמרא Gemara for the Christians, but the מאירי Meiri
says דלהלכה delehalacha that that was only talking about ancient pagans, but
non-Jews nowadays, of course you'd save their life on שבת. Shabbos. So
anyway, one way or another. But that's, but we're just going to
bracket that for a moment. The issue still here is that if
you're being a formalist, you would make a distinction, you'd say like
this, if the building collapses
and I don't know who was in the building, maybe there was
a Jew, maybe there was a non-Jew, fine, I'm going to, you
know, I'm going to uncover the rubble in order to save the
person's life. But here, it's not like, here, it starts by saying
twenty years ago we decided that your status was a non-Jew, right?
So then to ongoing then say, so then when the building collapses
I'll say that it collapsed on a non-Jew, it's not like, you
know, it's different, right? People sort of understand conceptually the difference between
saying maybe there was a Jew there, maybe there wasn't, if there
was a Jew there, so I don't say oh it's ninety percent
likely, the, you know, ten people walked in the building, nine walked
out, so it's only ten percent likely it's a Jew, I'm not
going to bother. No, the fact that it's ten percent likely you're
still going to go ahead and bother. That's one thing. But it's
very different when I've already determined this person's status twenty years ago
and I've, and הלכתית halachically categorized the person as a non-Jew, you
know, to still keep that ספק safek alive. And that's the, so
the interesting thing about this גמרא Gemara is that this גמרא Gemara
says even if that's true, even if the question of this person's
status and we've basically been deciding for the last twenty years he's
a non-Jew and we've been using him as our שבת גוי Shabbos
goy and we've been giving him all of our טרפה treifa food
and all these types of things, we keep on remembering that there's
a small likelihood that he actually is Jewish so we'll go ahead
and violate שבת Shabbos and save his life on שבת. Shabbos. So
it is interesting, I think, because that's, you know, not normally the
way הלכה halacha
would operate. We always, so there's always a possibility that anybody's Jewish
or just this one?
This one person because we didn't know his identity and we didn't
know who deposited him on the doorstep. So even though, but again
that's the interesting thing, right? For every other thing we've been treating
him as a non-Jew, but we remember we don't in the end
of the day know who his parents are, so when it comes
to this issue of saving his life, we're going to remember that.
Okay, that's interesting.
It's like the ספק safek we had a couple of days ago,
right? Where there's like different, that the ספק safek, doesn't survive different
generations.
Right, exactly. So that's fascinating that the גמרא Gemara is willing to
say that since under other cases we don't go by אחר הרוב,
achar harov, here too we would keep that possibility alive, excuse the
pun. Whatever, keep, but we would still remember that many, many years
later and therefore that would have and, and it would not stop
us, and you know, therefore, you know, it would have implications in
terms of saving the life on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so I just
have to tell, since we're talking about this very difficult concept of
not saving the life of a non-Jew on שבת, Shabbos, at least
what it is in principle if not in practice. So there's a
story that, that about,
about a Professor Lieberman, Saul Lieberman who was walking with somebody and...
I forget who I forget who they told us who it was
that he was walking with. He was but some colleague, non-Jewish,
philosopher, somebody who really
knew,
knew rabbinic literature, and he said to him as they were walking
together on שבת Shabbos and he said to him, so tell me,
if this building were to collapse on me, would you save my
life? So Professor שמואל Shmuel Lieberman said, yes. So he said, would
you save my life because that's the הלכה, halacha, would you save
my life because of דרכי שלום? darchei shalom? So he said, no,
no, no, I'd save your life because that's the הלכה. halacha. All
right, so he was very satisfied, so he left, and then the
student said, what do you mean that's the הלכה? halacha? He said,
I just told him that because of דרכי שלום. darchei shalom.
All right, anyway,
so now the גמרא Gemara, continues. Okay, so אלא, so how do
you understand שמואל'ס Shmuel's statement that for פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, אלא
כי איתמר דשמואל ארישא איתמר, ella ki itmar deShmuel areisha itmar, it
was said on the first part of the statement. אם רוב עובדי
כוכבים עובדי כוכבים, im rov ovdei kochavim ovdei kochavim, if the majority
are non-Jews, you assume that he's a non-Jew in the city. אמר
שמואל ולפקח עליו את הגל אינו כן, amar Shmuel ulefake'ach alav es
hagal eino kein, but that wouldn't be true to save his life
on שבת, Shabbos, then you would still maintain the possibility that he
might be Jewish.
So if the building collapsed on this one particular— Exactly.
Okay. Now, אם רוב עובדי כוכבים עובדי כוכבים למאי הלכתא? im rov
ovdei kochavim ovdei kochavim lemai hilchasa? Okay, so now we know that
we're going to assume (a) we're always going to save his life
on שבת, Shabbos, (b) if the majority is Jewish we have our
responsibility of להחיותו. lehachayoso.
So for what purposes are we going to assume he's non-Jewish? So
it would seem the answer's obvious. Number one is we don't have
a special responsibility to provide for him and so on, not להחיותו,
lehachayoso, but the גמרא Gemara has a more extreme example. למאי הלכתא?
lemai hilchasa? אמר רב פפא להאכילו נבלות, amar Rav Papa leha'achilo neveilos,
in order to go ahead and feed him treif, you could use
him as a שבת גוי, Shabbos goy, you could feed him treif,
you can totally assume that he's non-Jewish even in an active way
of
which we would never allow if we had a doubt that he
was a Jew, because you're causing a Jew to sin. Okay, so
that's if the majority is non-Jew. Okay, אם רוב ישראל ישראל למאי
הלכתא? im rov Yisrael Yisrael lemai hilchasa? Now, if it's fifty-fifty, we
already assume he's ספק ישראל safek Yisrael and we have a responsibility
להחיותו. lehachayoso. So how does it matter when you go from fifty-fifty
and you wouldn't obviously feed him treif if it's fifty-fifty? So how
does it matter when you go from fifty-fifty to the majority? How
does it matter when you move from ספק ישראל safek Yisrael to
ודאי ישראל? vadai Yisrael? What difference does it make? Okay, so the
גמרא says, אמר רב פפא להחזיר לו אבידה, amar Rav Papa lehachazir
lo aveida, to return the lost object. Because why would that matter?
Because first of all,
when we get to בבא מציעא Bava Metzia we'll see that the
גמרא has some concerns about returning lost objects to a non-Jew. So
you might have thought he's a ספק, safek if it's fifty-fifty ספק
non-Jew I shouldn't return the אבידה, aveida, but more easily, without getting
into that, you could just say that it's like המוציא מחבירו עליו
הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. I found this lost object. If you're
a Jew I have a responsibility to return it to you. If
you're a non-Jew you don't. If it's fifty-fifty I will say, prove
to me you're Jewish, and if you can't prove to me you're
Jewish, המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. Okay, again, תוספות
is a little funny because obviously it's a case that you know
that it's this other person's, and you're still saying it might be
yours but I don't have a responsibility to return it. All right,
anyway, so that's the נפקא מינה. nafka mina. So if it's fifty-fifty
you don't have to return it, but you still have all these
other responsibilities in terms of assuming this person is a Jew. But
when it comes to דיני ממונות, dinei mamonos, we would say המוציא
מחבירו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. Okay, so now the גמרא
says like this, מחצה על מחצה ישראל למאי הלכתא? mechetza al mechetza
Yisrael lemai hilchasa? For what הלכה halacha fifty-fifty do you assume he's
a Jew? Now again, רש"י Rashi tells us point out you had
all the things we said before: להחיותו, lehachayoso, not to feed him
treif, not to cause him other עבירות, aveiros, right? But the גמרא
is still going to give an example here about a דיני ממונות
dinei mamonos type of a case. So אמר ריש לקיש לנזיקין. amar
Reish Lakish linezikin. When it comes to damages. היכי דמי, heichi dami,
what's the
scenario? אילימא דנגחה תורא דידן לתורא דידיה, eileima denagcha tora didan letora
dideih, if our ox gored his ox—this week's פרשה, parsha, last week's
פרשה—so parsha what's the הלכה? halacha? The הלכה halacha is if an
ox of a Jew gores the ox of another Jew, if it's
a habitual one it pays full, if it's a non-habitual one it
pays half. Whereas the גמרא says that
by—again, this is a nice distillation in this one דף of all
of the sort of distinctions in law between Jews and non-Jews, all
the ones
that raise ethical issues. So the גמרא assumes though that if the
ox of a Jew gores a non-Jew,
then it always works to the disadvantage of a non-Jew. If an
ox of a Jew gores a non-Jew, you never pay anything, and
if the ox of a non-Jew gores a Jew, you always pay
full amount. Okay, by the way, since we're talking about that פסוק
pasuk and talking about whether it's talking about a Jew or not,
like the פסוק pasuk says כי יגח שור איש את שור רעהו
ומת, ki yigach shor ish es shor re'eihu vames, if a man's
ox gores his neighbor's ox and he dies. Okay, and that basis
of the word רעהו re'eihu is the base on which חז"ל Chazal
say only the ox of a fellow Jew, not the ox of
a non-Jew, would be a different הלכה. halacha. Anyway, so אבן עזרא
Ibn Ezra quotes a קראי Karai who explains the פסוק pasuk כי
יגח שור איש את שור רעהו, ki yigach shor ish es shor
re'eihu, if an ox gores his fellow ox. שור רעהו. shor re'eihu.
So then אבן עזרא Ibn Ezra says with such a good line,
he says,
a שור shor doesn't have a רע, rei'a, a friend, except— This
guy, this commentator who said who gave it this explanation, no אין
לשור רעיה אלא הוא. Ein l'shor re'aya ela hu. Okay, anyway, fine.
All right, so you guys are too good, you're ruining my punchlines.
Anyway, so the גמרא says like this: what's the case? אי נימא
דנכח תורא דידן לתורא דידיה, Ei neima d'nacha tora didan l'tora didey,
our ox gored his ox. So if he's not Jewish it should
be zero, if he's Jewish it should be full or half. לימא
ליה, Leima lei, so if it's only, so say to him,
אייתי ראיה דישראל את ושקול, Aiti raya d'Yisrael at v'shkol, go prove
that you are, if it's 50/50,
go prove that you're a Jew. And you can't prove it. המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi m'chavero alav h'raya. You might be a non-Jew,
I'm not going to pay you. לא צריכא דנכח תורא דידיה לתורא
דידן. Lo tzricha d'nacha tora didey l'tora didan. His ox gored our
ox and it's a תם. Tam. So פלגא משלם. Palga m'shalem. He
pays 50 percent, that's what he would be assuming he's Jewish. ואידך
פלגא, V'idach palga, the other 50, אמר להו, Amar l'hu, he says,
אייתי ראיה דלאו ישראל אנא, Aiti raya d'lav Yisrael ana, if you
want me to pay full, prove I'm not a Jew, ואתן לכון,
V'intein l'chon, and then I'll give it to you. All right, so
anyway, בקיצור, B'kitzur, basically if it's 50/50 we assume he's Jewish, except,
you know, whether in terms of our obligations of להחיותו, L'hachayoto, whether
in terms of obviously not giving him טרפות Treifos and the other
things. The only questions become like דיני ממונות Dinei mamonot issues of
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi m'chavero alav h'raya. Less that we, if
it's more likely he's not Jewish we assume he's non-Jewish, we can
even ask him to do מלאכה Melacha on שבת Shabbos and feed
him טרפות. Treifos. And the only one thing is that we maintain
the memory that he might be Jewish for these הלכות Halachos in
terms of לפקח עליו את הגל. L'fakeyach alav et h'gal. So that
was the end of that, but again the general rule that we
go by רוב except for יוחסין Yuchsin where we need more than
a רוב, the חומרא Chumra of יוחסין Yuchsin not to draw conclusions
that are logical from that משנה. Mishna הדרן עלך בתולה נישאת. Hadran
alach Betula Nisat. Let's end today by reading the first משנה of
the next פרק. Perek. האשה שנתאלמנה או נתגרשה. Ha'isha she'nitalmena o nitgarsha.
Now we get from a debate about were you a virgin on
the wedding night to that which is טענת בתולים, Ta'anat betulim, we
get to a question about many years later, 20 years later they're
getting divorced and the debate was whether you, whether we, whether it
was a first marriage or a second marriage. Nobody has saved the
כתובה, Ketubah, they didn't frame it and put it on the wall.
So the question is, does she collect 100 or 200? So was
this a first marriage or not? האשה שנתאלמנה או נתגרשה. Ha'isha she'nitalmena
o nitgarsha. היא אומרת Hi omeret she says, בתולה נשאתני, Betula nisatani,
he married me when I was a virgin. והוא אומר לא כי
אלא אלמנה נשאתיך, V'hu omer lo ki ela almana nesatich, I married
you when you were a widow. So it wasn't a question was
she a virgin on the wedding night in the sense of like
we didn't know if she had had sex before, it was a
question of whether it was a first marriage or a second marriage.
And you
know like this is 20 years later, so let's find out. אם
יש עדים שיצתה בהינומא. Im yesh edim she'yatzta b'hinuma. Now we're going
to find out what were the practices that they would do for
a first wedding. If there were witnesses that she went out בהינומא,
B'hinuma, it's a type of like a wedding carriage with, you know,
we'll talk about what exactly בהינומא B'hinuma is, וראשה פרוע, V'rosha parua,
her head was uncovered, and רש"י Rashi also says it means like
her hair was like flowing down on her shoulders. All of those
things would be particular things which it signals, we'll have a fun
time looking at this in the גמרא, that this was a first
wedding. Then כתובתה מאתים. Ketubatah matayim. The כתובה Ketubah is 200. רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר אף חילוק קליות ראיה. Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka
omer af chiluk kalyot raya. Even the distributing of like, of like
parched wheat, corn, or whatever, which is a special thing that they
would do for a סימן טוב, Siman tov, like like he said,
even if they threw rice, you know, throw, you know, whatever. Or
we would say wearing a white wedding gown, you know, other types
of things, just other types of מנהגים, Minhagim, although white wedding gown
might more similarly be to הינומא, Hinuma, although I think the whole
white wedding gown is also influenced by the Christians and the non-Jews,
it should be
אסור Assur because of
בחוקותיהם, B'chukoteihem, but okay, that's a different discussion. Everybody wears one even
a second wedding. Okay, it should be אסור Assur because of בחוקותיהם,
B'chukoteihem, but okay, that's a different discussion. Anyway, אף חילוק קליות ראיה,
Af chiluk kalyot raya, even just the handing out of those like
parched corn is a proof that or roasted corn is a type
of thing they would do at a first wedding. ומודי רבי יהושע.
U'modeh Rabbi Yehoshua. Now, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua concedes. Now where's רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua conceding? Presumably this is רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua from
the previous משנה from the previous פרק. Perek. Remember that רבי יהושע
Rebbi Yehoshua's says we don't believe her when she when it's a
he said she said. So even though רבי יהושע says we don't
believe her when she makes certain claims, he does believe that sometimes
we believe what somebody is saying. What would be the case? באומר
לחברו, B'omer l'chavero, somebody said to his friend, שדה זו של אביך
הייתה ולקחתיה הימנו. Sadei zu shel avicha hayta u'lekachtiya heimenu. This field,
by the way, you should know, the field that I'm on originally
it was your father's and I purchased it from him. In that
case, נאמן, Ne'eman, he's believed, שהפה שאסר הוא הפה שהתיר. She'hapeh she'asar
hu hapeh she'hitir. The same mouth that made it forbidden, remember his
phrase was לא מפיה אנו חיים. Lo mipia anu chayim. We don't
live from her mouth. But here we do live from this guy's
mouth because without his first claim we wouldn't have any reason to
have thought it was originally the other guy's field. So when your
very mouth makes, you know, sort of is what gets you into
the hole, it can get you out of the hole as well.
שהפה שאסר, She'hapeh she'asar, the same mouth that made it forbidden is
the mouth that made it permissible. ואם יש עדים שהיא של אביו,
V'im yesh edim she'hi shel aviv, however if it goes back to
the case of where the presumption is the other way, there were
witnesses that the field originally was this guy's, was was this guy's
father's,
then... And then he says, by the way, I purchased it from
your father, אינו נאמן, Eino ne'eman, he's not believed. So that's no,
that's well, possibly everybody, but that's again within רבי יהושע saying we
don't believe you סתם stam when you make claims. If, however, it's
a פה שאסר פה שהתיר, peh she'asar peh she'hitir, then we will
believe you. But that's the רבי יהושע approach, that we don't believe
her when she makes claims why he said she said, she's trying
to extract money from him. She does not have a presumption of
being believed. The only time we would believe somebody is if they
basically had already conceded the point. Okay, so we will see the
גמרא on this tomorrow.
The פה שאסר פה שהתיר peh she'asar peh she'hitir could apply to
her also, in terms of her claim.